[Music]
this program is brought to you by
Stanford University please visit us at
stanford.edu
I I just want to do one thing actually
before we start the uh the material of
the
Class A whole bunch of people a lot of
people particularly people from Europe
who actually follow these things on the
Internet seem very puzzled they send me
email even some of my friends in Europe
who are physicists who are following it
uh are very curious about what's going
on here they don't see you people they
only see me and they know that I'm
teaching a class in this or that special
uh special Topic in classical mechanics
or whatever and they can sense that
there's something a little bit different
about it they can sense that it's not a
standard um undergraduate or graduate
course
in these subjects and they ask me what
is this what is this about or who are
these people you're teaching to they can
tell
it and most of them don't know what
continuing education means they didn't
know what it meant and so they asked me
I thought I would tell them uh over the
uh over the um internet what this class
is it's continuing education which means
education for people not from
Stanford people not oh they can be from
Stanford some of the people probably are
either employed by Stanford maybe were
students at Stanford but um almost
everybody in this class is a little bit
too old to be an undergraduate
student even a little bit too old to be
a graduate student they're people from
the community from paloalto from
Mountain View from uh who lives further
than Mountain View okay what's the
furthest come for
this where forer City okay so that's 20
miles away so people from within a
certain radius I don't know whatever the
radius is are allowed to come and take
courses at Stanford they pay a bit of
money for it and a professor teaches
them now this is not it is most
definitely not your standard freshman
physics there's another guy on the
internet who teaches freshman physics
and told he does it very well that's not
what this is this is The Real McCoy
theoretical physics at the full scale
level we use equations we not only use
equations we sometimes use hard
equations but we tend to try to use the
simplest equations that will do the
job basically we try to keep it
minimal uh just out of curiosity I I
more or less know the answer just by
looking but what the age distribution of
people here is by compar is there
anybody here under
40 yeah there's uh there's maybe one
handful of people under 40 incidentally
for those who can't see the audience
there's probably about a 100 people in
the room I'm not sure it's a it's a
small
theater uh with a lot of seats it's uh a
lecture theater more or less filled up
and
um maybe four or five or three or four
people were under
40 let's see let's go to the other end
how many people here are over
70 a good deal more maybe uh 10 or 12
anybody over 80 we got a couple of
people over 80 anybody over 90 this time
oh there have been people over 90
they're having people over 90 in this
class so you see the age distribution is
such that
basically
people want to get to the basic ideas
fast they don't have a hell of a lot of
time they want to get there
fast
so I try to tell them in some minimal
way what the basic things you really
have to know in order to get on to the
next thing sometimes the basic things
that you need to know are a little more
difficult a little more elaborate
we do them anyway we do them as
efficiently and as straightforwardly and
with the minimal amount of stuff uh to
to get them right to get them really
right not metaphor not uh not the
analogy but equations when
necessary
um what else can I say about this
class I guess it has various names
Quantum mechan the physics 25 I'm
inclined to call it quantum mechanics
old
people including
myself anyway the first course in the
series let me just uh say what the
outline of the whole course of courses
is these series of courses will consist
of about six 10 lecture
series the first of which was in
classical
mechanics the classical mechanics is the
basic basis of all classical physics
classical means before quantum
mechanics anything that doesn't involve
quantum mechanics or which ignores
quantum mechanics or which is in a range
of
parameters where quantum mechanics can
be replaced by basic
classical logic that's called classical
physics physics so the first class was
classical mechanics which is in some
sense the basis for all of physics the
motion of objects uh the energy of
objects the momentum of objects what the
characteristic behavior of uh systems is
as they evolve with time and so forth we
discussed that last quarter and anybody
who is thinking of following these
classes should begin with that the next
class which is already on the internet
was called I believe quantum
entanglement now this is also a class on
quantum mechanics and it will be
self-contained but I would strongly
advise anybody who's following to go to
course number two was it called quantum
entanglement does anybody remember I
think it was called quantum entanglement
it is also on the internet it was the
first one that was on the internet and
uh to get that that under your belt
first before attempting to do the
fullscale quantum mechanics that we're
going to do here although what I'm going
to do is pretty
self-contained I'm going to start this
evening with some basic thoughts about
the Deep
differences in the logic of classical
mechanics and quantum
mechanics or classical
maybe even mechanics is too strong a
word classical physics and Quantum Mech
and quantum
physics there are some very queer
phenomena in quantum physics that don't
exist in classical physics now one of
them is the fact that quantum mechanics
is based on statistical thinking
Randomness a certain degree of um not
imprecision that's not the right word a
certain degree of uh nondeterministic or
indeterministic behavior
unpredictability that's the word I'm
looking for
unpredictability but it's a special kind
of
unpredictability Einstein famously said
God does not play
dice Neil's bore told him Einstein don't
tell God what to
do but in fact in a sense God I I don't
know if there's a God I when I I use the
word God in the same
sense that physicists always use it
meaning uh the laws of physics or
something like that the laws of physics
don't play dice at least not in the
standard sense let me imagine for you a
theory that's based on a bit of
Statistics which is not the way quantum
mechanics works and then I'll illustrate
it for you by showing you some of the
differences imagine that there was a
element of Randomness in in Newton's Law
whatever which law f equals ma together
with the law of um of gravity all right
so F equal ma together with the law of
gravity tells us how objects move let us
say how the moon moves around the earth
and it predicts with infinite Precision
if you could work out the equations with
infinite precision and if you could
account for every detail of the Earth
and the moon and all the Mater material
that's in between and so forth uh it
would predict with enormous
detail deterministically the motion of
the Moon which means if you know where
the moon starts and you know how the
Moon is moving in the beginning then you
can predict Forever After exactly how
the moon moves around the earth that's
the deterministic classical mechanics
now let me imagine a modification and
the modification involves a little bit
of
Randomness for example
okay so let's imagine God sitting on his
throne throwing dice every tenth of a
second God throws the dye and if he gets
Snake Eyes what he does is he gives the
moon a little extra push in One
Direction if he gets a seven he pushes
the moon a little bit in the other
direction a degree of Randomness based
on the random throwing of dice and
really random random a really random
number
generator uh being used to put a little
bit of fluctuation into the motion of
the
Moon that sounds like it introduces the
kind of uncertainty the kind of uh thing
that one talks about in quantum
mechanics
uncertainty
um in non-predictability
unpredictability but it is not anything
like the randomness and unpredict ility
of quantum mechanics the randomness and
unpredictability of quantum mechanics is
exceedingly special exceedingly special
and exent quite different and it's that
that we want to get our head around and
learn and understand the difference
between these things uh By the time this
class is finished but also we want to
learn how to use quantum mechanics a
little bit to calculate some things um
let's notice one thing about this law
which which includes a little bit of
Randomness the throwing of dice in order
to uh to either kick the moon a little
bit or inhibit the Moon's motion a
little bit one of the things that would
do is to add a little bit of energy or
subtract a little bit of energy from the
motion of the Moon randomly if you
randomly give the moon a knock this way
and then a kick that way and a bonk that
way and keep doing it over and over
again each time you do it there on the
average it may not change the energy but
each little increment is randomly going
to either increase the energy or
decrease the energy of the
Moon and if you do that randomly
eventually that will build up to a
statistical Randomness in the energy in
other words energy would not be exactly
conserved in a world in which the laws
of motion included a little bit of
classical
Randomness I call it classical
Randomness uh to distinguish it from
Quantum
Randomness in quantum
mechanics you prepare a system the same
way that you might prepare the moon in
an initial situation you let it go for a
while and then you look at it and indeed
you
discover at the end of it that what you
measure is a little bit
unpredictable but you also find that
energy is exactly
conserved no hint no Remnant at all of
energy being uh knocked this way and
knock that way if you start it with a
given energy with a given precise energy
and you let it evolve for a while and
you measure the energy later the energy
is exactly the same as you started with
so there's something funny about this
Randomness it seems to affect some
things and not other things and doesn't
work the way you might expect uh
randomness this in classical physics to
work let me give you two oh I think
three other examples of the oddness of
this
Randomness the first comes from an
experiment which to my mind shows the
weirdness of quantum mechanics in the
easiest and most straightforward least
difficult way much easier for my money
than Bells inequalities and all that
sort of stuff it's called a two slit
experiment all of you know about it or
most of you know about it if not you
learn about it right now but it is
extremely odd when compared with
classical uh
Randomness right so classical Randomness
just being this idea that every now and
then you give the system a little knock
the two- slit experiment involves a
source of particles those particles
could be photons they could be electrons
they could be neutrons they could be
bowling balls except the effect for
bowling balls is so minute that you'd
never be able to measure it so when we
speak about particles we think about
things which are very light and because
they're light the quantum effects
associated with them are significant and
measurable all right so we have a source
of some kind it could be a laser
shooting out photons but imagine the
photons are coming through one at a time
very small number of them uh Quant of
light one at a time one at a time one
every 5 minutes if you like I don't know
just to go to some extreme situation
these are the photons coming out of the
photon
gun and the photons pass through a ob
obstacle with a little hole in it all
right this is a two-dimensional diagram
of a three-dimensional
situation this blue object over here is
intended to be a disc with a tiny hole
in it so the photons can go
through uh and they come out the other
side of the a hole and when they come
out the other side of the hole they
eventually get to a screen over here
that screen records the photon by a
flash a flash of light at the screen not
the flash of the original photons but
another flash of energy appears at a
point on the screen and Records or it
could be just the blackening of a
photographic a photographic plate
something that records the position of
the photon when it goes through
here now first let's think
classically uh but classically with a
bit of Randomness the bit of Randomness
that we can imagine is that when the
photon goes through
here a little random kick might
influence the photon and either kick it
upwards or
downwards in fact by a random amount
what would we expect then well if there
was no Randomness then the photons would
go straight through and illuminate a
single point be completely deterministic
the photons would always arrive at
exactly the same point if the hole was
small enough and if the beam of photons
was narrow
enough but now we can imagine a random
kick what does the random kick do well
it changes the direction of the photon
of the photon not the whole Photon beam
but one Photon at a time it might kick
the first Photon up a little bit the
second Photon down and so forth and so
on eventually what you will
see is a
blob of Illumination on the screen over
here on the average the photon might go
straight ahead so the blob might be most
intense at the center it might be highly
improbable to knock the photon through
UH 60 or
70° so the signal would fade As you move
moved away from the center you would see
a blob with a maximum intensity near the
center and thinning out as you moved far
away and you might describe it by a
probability function the probability
function being the probability that the
photon arrives in different
places okay now we go oh now we do the
same thing in real quantum mechanics in
other words in the real world we see
essentially the same thing the photon go
through the
hole with no ability to control the
situation we find out that the photons
again create a blob like this but now
we're going to do something a little
different and I think everybody here
more or less more or less everybody
knows what I'm going to do I'm going to
open a second
hole okay but let's think about what
classical Randomness would do classical
Randomness would simply mean that we and
we'll also imagine that this beam of
photons is at its origin a little bit
uncertain and a little bit random so
that some photons begin a little bit
upward some photons a little bit
downward some photons go through the
upper hole some photons go through the
lower
hole if a photon goes through the upper
hole it may or may not get a random kick
and get knocked off off course if it
goes through the lower hole it also gets
a random kick now we're Imagining the
photons come through one at a time we
could even imagine
a it's
okay I do that all the time
uh where was I yes the photons get a
kick we're imagining that the photons
come through one at a time very sparsely
and so what one Photon does doesn't
influence a later Photon because the
later Photon comes through so much later
that whatever gave the first Photon a
kick is already finished happening and
it's waiting for the next uh throw of
the dice in fact the next Photon may
come through a 100 throws of the dice
later and so we expect the next
Photon uh to be random statistically
independent of the first photon
under those
circumstances what we would expect well
let's uh let's let's decide what we
would expect supposing only one hole is
open if only one hole was open then we
would see a blob of Illumination like
that with a profile that might look
something like that supposing we closed
up the first blob the first
hole and opened the second hole close
the first one open the second one all
right so first we begin with just one
hole
then we close the first hole and open
the second hole what would you expect to
see what you would expect to see under
those circumstances is a different blob
slightly displaced from the first
one the blue blob wouldn't be there
because we closed the first hole the
green blob would be there because we
opened the second
hole now what happens if we open both
holes what happens if you open both
holes in classical mechanic X is the
probability for a photon to get to the
screen at any given point is the sum of
the probabilities for it to get there by
either root the photon Photon can either
go through the upper root or it can go
through the lower
route if both holes are open the
probability to get to this point over
here let's call it the Green Point over
here the probability to get over there
is the probability to go through the
upper hole and arrive at the Green Point
Plus the probability to get to go
through the lower hole and arrive at the
Green Point so the result is in
classical physics you would always see
the signal over here the profile over
here just being the sum of the two
probability distributions and it would
look I wish I had another color they
never leave me enough colors all right
uh we would see something which would
look like
just a higher no no it would be much it
would be bigger than
that it would look like that and in
particular if there was any point over
here such that the photon could arrive
either from one hole or from the other
hole or both then we would find
illumination at that point for sure by
opening both
holes that's what classical log logic
let's let's call it by the right name
classical logic that's what classical
logic classical statistics classical
probability would dictate for a series
of
particles coming through here one at a
time when they come through one at a
time they make BLiP BLiP BLiP BLiP but
the average probability of the
distribution of blips would be a
distribution which would be the sum of
the two
distributions what happens if you really
do this experiment
you find what's called an interference
pattern the interference
pattern looks like
this well let's see let me get it
right in
particular oh first of all what is this
figure this figure is a probability
distribution and it tells you
the horizontal axis here tells you what
the probability of a photon getting to a
particular point at a particular height
here but in particular it says that
there are no photons which arrive at
that point there are no photons which
arrive at that point there are no
photons which arrive at that point this
is odd if you opened only one hole then
you would find a probability
distribution which wasn't zero in other
words you would find illumination at
that point point you open the other hole
you still find illumination at that
point you open both holes and all of a
sudden no Photon gets to that point even
though they're coming in coming through
once every 20 minutes or once every 20
years and therefore how can they know
about each other nevertheless if you
open both
holes there will be places where no
photons can get to despite the fact that
photons arrived at those points when
only one hole was
open that
is um you might be able to sit down and
work up some in some interesting but
rather elaborate mechanism to make this
happen you could imagine elaborate
complicated
mechanisms where uh somehow the
this this uh screen here some degrees of
freedom inside the screen remember how
many photons went through and they
remember what they're supposed to do but
it would be a rather elaborate mechanism
just for this one purpose this
phenomenon of interference of
destructive interference this is called
destructive
interference that the probabilities
cancel instead of adding at certain
points that's a very generic property in
uh in quantum
mechanics and and so it requires a kind
of explanation which is not some
detailed mechanical complicated
explanation it requires a a broad new
idea about how statistics works and how
about how the logic of um of quantum
mechanics works so that's the first
really weird thing that happens in
quantum mechanics now let me give you
another
example if you remember in last course
we talked a little bit about
reversibility we talked about the laws
of physics in particular we talked about
the laws of physics for discrete systems
for example uh we discussed the possible
laws of physics deterministic laws of
physics for a coin which can either be
heads or
tails now of course flipping the coin
that introduces a level of um of
uncertainty a level
of uh
statistics probability into things I
want to think about the deterministic
laws the truly deterministic laws are
the ones that whatever the coin is doing
it will tell you what the coin is doing
next so when we discussed this last
quarter we talked about two possible
laws of physics the first was that if
you find heads in the next instant when
you look at it after an instant of time
you'll find heads again if t Tails then
you find taals again then your laws of
physics just permit two possible um
Evolutions heads heads heads heads heads
heads heads or tails Tails Tails Tails
tails and the other possible laws of
physics or law of physics was that when
you see a head in the next instant
microsc or whatever your unit of time is
you will see the opposite Tails then the
two possible laws of physics are or the
two possible not laws of physics the two
possible evolutions one of them begins
with heads and goes heads Tails heads
Tails heads tails and the other one
begins with Tails and goes Tails heads
Tails heads Tails heads whether you know
it or not those two different things
were different they began one with heads
one with
Tails uh that was that was the basic
idea of a deterministic law of physics
now you can have of course more
complicated systems than there just two
State systems we imagine for example a
six-state system a six-state system was
a d a die that can be 1 2 3 4 5 six but
let's just take a simpler thing let's
take a coin with three sides if you
can't imagine a coin with three sides
then you'll have to do this using
abstract
mathematics okay a coin with three sides
has heads tails and what's what else
feet heads tails and feet all right
heads tails and
feet all right and there are two all
let's let's consider a simple law of
physics a simple law of physics could
tell you that whenever you have heads it
goes to Tails whenever you have tails it
goes to feet whenever you have feet it
goes to heads again and then wherever
you start you just cycle around
endlessly forever and ever now there's a
certain sense in which this is rever in
which this is what does it mean to say
it's
deterministic what does it mean to say
information is not lost in this process
what it means
is that no matter how long the system
evolves let's suppose you started with
heads and you let it go a million units
of
time it will just go around and around
in cycle if at the end of that you
reverse the law of physics now reversing
the law of physics just means having it
go in the opposite direction if you
could somehow press a button
or turn a knob which had the effect of
reversing the law of
physics in other words changing the
direction of every
arrow and think about actually if you
could really do this by pressing a
button change the law of physics then if
you allow the system to evolve for any
length of time at the end of that time
reverse it and let it evolve for the
same length of time again again guess
what it magically comes back to the same
original
configuration that's what it means to
say that physics is reversible or that's
what it means to say that information is
never lost in
physics that uh that no matter how long
you keep going if you revers if you
could find a way to reverse the laws of
physics and run them backward for the
same exact length of time you'll come
back to the starting configuration now
to do that you might not even need to
know the laws of physics you might need
to know very little the only thing you
would need to know is how to reverse the
law you need you needn't even know what
the law is whatever the law is if you
can find a button to push that reverses
it then you can test the determinism of
physics by simply starting someplace
letting it evolve for a long period of
time and then letting it evolved with
the reverse law of physics if you come
back to the same place every time then
your law of physics is
deterministic now what about a little
bit of classical probability a little
bit of deity playing
dice so let's suppose with some very
very small
probability the
deity does something different that's
not prescribed by the laws of physics
for example in some random way with a
probability of one in a million the law
might say don't move instead of moving
the way the diagram says stay
still if you allow the system to evolve
for a short period of
time then and then run it
backward it will go back to the same
point but if you allow it to run long
enough that there's a significant
statistical probability for a flux
uation for something to happen which is
not
deterministic in other words if it was
one in a million that you stand still
but you let the system run for 10
million units of time then guess what no
chance well not no chance you have a
chance that you'll come back to the same
point but you also have an equal chance
that you'll come back to any of the
other points in other words this test
will fail it'll
fail uh onethird of the time you will
come back to the same point 2/3 of the
time you will come back to two different
points so a little bit of
classical
Randomness
destroys
the
um what I called last quarter the
conservation of
probability no the conservation of
information information gets lost what
about quantum mechanics
is information lost well there is an
element of statistical things in quantum
mechanics when a electron goes through a
hole like
this it has a probability for getting
kicked up let's just take the case let's
simplify now this is the one slit
experiment we don't even need the two
slit experiment let's start with the one
slit
experiment the electron goes through the
slit It's aimed toward the slit
sometimes it more or less goes straight
through sometimes it gets kicked up a
little bit sometimes it gets kicked down
a little bit and you might think that
this is more or less like throwing
dice in fact if you look for the
electron afterwards if you look for the
electron out
here after you've given it time to pass
through at the moment now let's just
send one electron through one electron
if we send one electron
through it may get kicked up it may go
straight through or it may get kicked
down if we do the same experiment
repeatedly which is of course is the
same thing as sending many electrons
through but if we do the same experiment
uh repeatedly we will find some go up
some go down some
uh but now let's ask the following
question supposing after a period of
time we send an electron through one
electron after a certain period of time
having given given it enough time to get
to the other side but not but let's
remove the screen over here let's remove
the screen send the electron through it
goes through comes out someplace
else but we don't look at it we don't we
don't bother detecting where the
electron is instead we just reverse the
law of physics we do what we did over
here reverse the direction of time if
you like can you really do this can you
really is there really a but a button
that you can push is there really
something that you can do to a system
that will reverse the motion yes in many
systems there is in many systems we
actually know how to manipulate the
system how to change magnetic fields how
to do things to a system of electrons so
as to run it backward so let's take it
as a uh as a given that after a certain
amount of time somebody can press the
button Buton that reverses the law of
physics that reverses the direction of
time so to speak and runs the system
backward for the same length of time
what
happens does that
electron we're not going to look at it
but do we later after after the end of
the
experiment we allow it to evolve for a
Time T and then we allow it to evolve
backward for another time T 2 T
altogether do we find the electron
moving backward along the original
trajectory or do we find the probability
the fluctuations
compounding and that after we turn it
around there's even worse
fluctuation particle comes through gets
knocked up we run it backward it either
gets knocked down or Knocked
Up which is it does it does does it
reverse precisely along the original
trajectory every single time or does the
statistical
fluctuation the imprecision the uh the
unpredictability in One Direction adds
to the unpredictability and going
backward and make it even U more
unpredictable afterwards than it was to
begin
with the answer is very curious
the answer is that if we don't look at
the
system in the intermediate stage after
it's gone through the hole over here do
don't look at it means don't interfere
with the electron in any
way take that screen away that might
have converted that electron into a
little pulse of light just remove any
influence on the electron over here
completely do not look at it do not
interfere with it do not do anything to
disturb it but just run the law of
physics backward then we will exactly
every single time detect the electron
running back along the reverse
trajectory on the other side over here
in particular we'll find the electron
just going right back into the
gun what if somebody does look at the
electron when it goes through to the
side over here for example supposing
somebody sets up an electron detector
which detects where the electron is and
then lets it
go having reversed the law of physics we
look at it and then reverse the law of
physics now in this case over here the
case where we're talking about classical
coins looking at a thing doesn't disturb
it very much if I have a
coin where's my coin I've lost my
coin it's okay it's only a Chilean
peso I lost my Chilean
Peso I think it was actually 100
pesos okay now here's my chile and peso
I put it down and I put it down heads
don't look at it now I look at it it
would be rather amazing if just the
process of looking at it was capable of
flipping it from heads to tails now of
course if I look at it with an intense
enough uh high frequency light beam a
beam of very very energetic photons sure
enough an energetic Photon could uh
could hit the coin knock it into the air
and spin it over that's true but you but
in classical physics you can look at an
object and determine its state determine
the heads or talsness of it with an
arbitrarily gentle
interaction and so by looking at a
system in classical mechanics and
looking at it with a very very gentle
apparatus or very gentle Photon or
whatever you like it does not entail
disturbing the system so if you look at
it after you allowed it to go a million
times and then reverse the law it will
have no effect no detrimental effect on
the experiment and you will come back to
the same uh to the same point that you
started
with right so just looking at the system
in between has no effect no does not
necessarily have an effect on it even
though whoever looks at it can
determine after a
million units of time where the system
is here looking at it has no effect on
what happens after you run it backward
exactly the opposite in quantum
mechanics if you detect the object if
you do anything to detect the
object electron in this case and then
run the law of physics backward what
you'll find out is that the
the probabilistic character of it gets
compounded so the fluctuation that sent
it up here when you run it backward and
you now know that it came out up here
and you run it backward it's likely to
come out down here or up here and it
will disturb the system in such a way
that the test of reversibility will
fail so this is
curious that uh that whatever Quantum
logic
is the questions of the kind we're
asking are deeply dependent on a
ridiculous question did somebody look at
the system uh during the course of its
Evolution and as I said of course
looking at a system can disturb it but
in classical physics we can look at a
system without disturbing it we can look
at a system detect the system measure
the system as gently as we like
arbitrarily Gent ly and have arbitrarily
small effect on it so that running it
backwards will be exactly as if we
didn't look at it not so in quantum
mechanics determining the state of a
system is never a small thing to do to
the system and this is an example it
completely destroys the uh the
experiment the two slit experiment has
also a similar
uh a
uh a similar story that goes with it
the story that I told you a moment ago
about the interference pattern and the
destructive interference is only
true if nobody records which way the
electron went through now when I say
nobody I don't mean a human being
necessarily I mean that nothing in the
environment of the experiment records
and remembers which way the went through
in other words after the experiment
there is nothing in the environment of
this experiment which has recorded which
way the electron went through nothing in
here only no this hasn't this also
hasn't recorded way the electron went
through if nothing records where the
electron goes through then there's an
interference pattern but if you were to
put a little demon over there a real
physical demon a real physical demon
could be another electron it could be uh
some uh some gas in the apparatus some
gas molecules in the
apparatus uh whatever it
is in such a way that something records
which way the electron went
through some something remembers it
afterwards perhaps a molecule over here
gets Disturbed gets excited if the
electron goes through the upper
hole gets excited and uh changes the
character of that molecule if it goes
through the lower hole it changes the
character of a different molecule so
looking afterwards after the electron
went through you can tell which hole the
electron went through then the
interference pattern is destroyed and
the answer is exactly the same as the
classical answer namely the
probabilities add just exactly as in
classical
physics so again
there's no way to record whether the
electron went through the upper hole or
the lower hole without seriously
disturbing the experiment without so
seriously disturbing the experiment that
you drastically can CH change the
conclusion that's a
Quantum
that's roughly speaking the general
character of quantum mechanics that you
cannot do measurements on systems
without disturbing them and disturbing
them can change completely the character
of a yak
question
yeah
yeah that is yeah that's a very very
good question that's an excellent
outstanding question
uh wish I knew the answer no I know the
answer
um yeah I will uh the answer answer has
to do with the probability distribution
for the position of the uh of the um of
the let's call this the detector let's
call this the detector okay now if the
detector is very well localized in space
as it would be if there were a heavy
massive classical
detector then by the uncertainty
principle which we haven't talked about
yet
if we're going to let me skip ahead
imagine that we have talked about the
uncertainty principle that's a
sophisticated question so I suspect you
you've thought about it a little bit if
the position of this detector the up
down position of this detector Delta X
is very very
small that means that the uncertainty in
the momentum of the detector is
large okay that means if I were to plot
the probability distribution of the
momentum of the
detector let's plot the probability
distribution of the momentum of the
detector it's rather
broad because for a heavy detector its
location is so well defined all right
now the electron comes through and kicks
the plate kicks this thing a little bit
it gives it a small kick and what does
it do it shifts this probability
distribution a small
amount but unless the probability
distribution has been
shifted by something approximately equal
to its width then you can't tell
afterwards whether it got a kick or not
you have to be uh in order to be able to
be certain that it got a kick you have
to kick it by an amount large by
comparison with the
uncertainty so it's the uncertainty
principle that comes in and resks you
resc rescues you or rescuse me and make
sure that the interference pattern is
not
destroyed okay the uncertainty principle
itself so let's go to the uncertainty
principle since it's been raised since I
raised
it the uncertainty principle is another
factor in quantum mechanics which is
extremely
different uh than physic than classical
physics conceptually very different I
know we haven't talked about the what
the uncertainty principle is yet but uh
let's uh let's discuss it anyway
let's Jump
Ahead my main motivation now is
to explain the strangeness of not to
explain the strangeness of quantum
mechanics but to point some fingers at
the strangeness of quantum
mechanics uh so that you see that it
really is fundamentally logically
different than classical mechanics
logically different whole logic of
quantum mechanics is different okay it's
easy to imagine a bit of uncertainty In
classical physics as I said the the uh
the coin throwing or the dice throwing
deity who sticks his finger into the
system and gives it a push this way a
push that way and so forth and that way
things after a short period of time
become
uncertain and it's easy to imagine that
that uncertainty can affect both
position and
momentum and if you wait a little while
both the position and the momentum may
be uncertain certain in fact if you wait
a little bit more than a tiny fraction
of a second for for a particle you might
discover that inevitably both the
position and the momentum get jostled
about and so that there's a good deal or
a certain amount of of uncertainty in
position and uncertainty in
momentum but you would be unlikely to
say that that uncertainty and position
and
momentum is um what's the word I'm
looking for
uh well first of all that it's
fundamental in any sense you would say
it was a result of hitting the system
randomly but I think most of us would
agree that under those
circumstances it was a bit of laziness
that didn't allow us to watch the
particle carefully enough to see what
exactly the momentum was and the
position was we always imagine in that
kind of classical context an example of
that classical context would be the
random walk of a Brownian moving
particle right so if we if we watch a
whole bunch of particles a whole bunch
of particles might form a cloud and that
cloud might spread and perhaps even the
velocity of the cloud or the the cloud
describing the velocities might also
spread but every one of those particles
if we cared to we could look at with
better Precision better and better
Precision we could look at it gently as
gently as we liked In classical physics
and determine both its velocity and its
position
simultaneously uh certainly that would
be true of a classical Brownie and
motion particle that was being knocked
around by uh by ordinary collisions with
uh some gas or something like that in
principle we can just get ourselves a
better microscope better uh better
accuracy better Precision better
resolving power
and do it very gently so as not to
disturb the system when we measure the
position we don't want to jostle the
momentum when we measure the momentum we
don't want to do something funny to the
position and we just measure it gently
enough so that we measure both the
position and the momentum that would be
expected to be true for a brownan
particle so the uncertainty in position
and momentum is something which in a
certain sense is due to our own laziness
and not spending enough money and buying
a good enough detector and so forth uh
to to be able to detect both the
position and the velocity at the same
time uh on the other hand in quantum
mechanics there's a really
fundamental obstruction a logical
obstruction a deep obstruction to
knowing to ever being able to measure
both the position and the velocity of a
particle I'm going to work it out for
you and show you how it works I'm going
to show you how Heisenberg first thought
about
it well he first thought about it
entirely through abstract mathematics
for us that's going to come later but
then when questioned by bore what are
you talking about that you can't measure
the position and the velocity
simultaneously your mathematics is a is
a Croc of balone don't tell me that x *
p is not equal to P * X come on that's
like saying 3 * 5 is not 5 * 3 did I
write it right yeah not equal two don't
tell me such nonsense stories give me
some physics and so Heisenberg cooked up
his experiment to
show uh to illustrate the fact not show
but illustrate the fact that there was a
good deep uh consistent reason why it's
impossible to ever ever under any
circumstances simultaneously determine
the position and the momentum of an
object so let's go through that a little
bit it has a similar character to some
of the other illustrations that I've
given
here what Heisenberg and bour and
Einstein and all those people knew
around
1926 was the property of photons in fact
whenever they thought about measuring
the properties of a particle they were
always thinking roughly speaking of
looking at it under a mic rcope
detecting it by bombarding it with
photons now it doesn't matter whether
they were photons or not it's just that
they were thinking about microscopes and
they were thinking in a language uh
where you optically look at things
doesn't have to be Optical but this is
what they were thinking so Heisenberg
imagined putting his particle under a
microscope and detecting its position
and its velocity and seeing what he
could
learn okay the measurement involved
interacting with a particle with a
photon a photon would be the thing which
would be used to determine the position
of momentum in other words looking at it
really meant hitting it with some light
letting the light scatter off and then
focusing the light waves focusing the
light waves in order to see exactly
where the particle was just as you would
do it for a billiard ball or for
anything else Focus the light on your
retina Focus the light on some screen
and construct the position of the
particle uh that was uh what they were
thinking about okay now here's what
Einstein and the brogley and others had
taught them about
photons first of all Einstein had told
them that the energy of a
photon is equal to Plank's
constant times the frequency of the
light describing the
photon uh this is equivalent
to Plank's other constant H
Bar times the angular frequency where F
stands for the frequency of a wave
number of cycles per second measured in
hertz okay usually a frequency of a
light wave is a lot of Herz how many
hertz how many 10 to the 15th for
ordinary light but it's just a number 10
to the 15th Herz Omega is the same as
the frequency except multiply by 2 pi
it's the angular frequency instead of
the um instead of the number of cycles
per second right and H bar is just H
divided by 2 pi so these are the same
Expressions I'll use this one over here
for the moment energy is equal to H *
frequency that's something that was
known by
Einstein now here's another fact about a
beam beam of light beams of Light have
not only energy but they also have
momentum you can take a beam of light
and shine it on something and it will
warm it it will heat it that tells you
what has energy but you can also take a
beam of light and you can shine it at
that door and if the beam of light has
sufficient intensity it'll just push the
door open in other words the beam of
light has
momentum uh so that when it when the
door absorbs the beam of light the door
gets a
kick just just as if uh just as if you
threw a ball at the door and the door
collide with the
ball it has momentum okay now what is
the relationship between the energy of a
beam of light and its momentum I'll just
tell you what it is this is this is
classical Maxwell theory of light uh if
a beam of light moving in a particular
direction assum it's moving in a
particular
direction has energy e
then it also has
momentum and the relationship is that
the energy is the speed of light times
the
momentum incidentally let's just check
the units of that equation in another
way let's compare that with Newton's
uh theory of momentum and energy for an
ordinary particle the energy is p ^2 / 2
m
that's non-
relativistic the momentum p^2 2 m yeah
that's that's good which is
equal to P * p over M and an extra 1/
[Music]
2 12 momentum * momentum / velocity now
what's momentum divided by velocity
sorry momentum divid by Mass
velocity so this is equal to 12 momentum
time
velocity well it's almost the same for a
photon there's a it's not the same
because we have to use the theory of
relativity for a photon but the
correction from the theory of relativity
is not so uh so enormous this is 1/2 the
velocity of the particle times its
momentum this is just equal to the
velocity of the particle time the
momentum so for highly relativistic
particles the formula is very similar
except the half goes away among other
things this argument tells you that the
units are right energy is velocity time
momentum um let me just solve
that momentum is energy divided by the
speed of
light we can now plug in and find that
the momentum of a photon or momentum of
any little piece of light let's do a
single photon now the energy of the
photon is H *
F uh and so the momentum is H * the
frequency divided by the speed of
light now if you have a wave that's
moving with a speed of
light you have a way of moving with a
speed of light it's moving down and it
has a certain frequency and a velocity
there's a
connection between the frequency and and
the uh between the frequency and the
wavelength think about it for for a
moment here's a
wavelength let's call the wavelength
Lambda Lambda is a standard uh is a
standard notation for the wavelength of
light the wavelength of
anything how far does the wave move in
one
cycle the answer is Lambda that's what
Lambda is it's the distance that the
wave moves in one cycle if you stand
there with your nose watching that light
Ray and it's moving past you all right
it moves past you one wavelength per
cycle one wavelength per unit per per
cycle how long does a cycle take how
long does one cycle take what's the
period that goes with one
cycle the inverse of the uh of the
frequency so the time that it takes the
time that it takes to move distance
Lambda is one over the
frequency so let's just write that down
time to go one cycle is equal to one
over the frequency the distance that it
goes in that same time is just Lambda so
what's the velocity of the wave the
velocity of the wave is the distance
that it goes divided by the time that it
travels distance over time
velocity C is equal to
Lambda / T which means Lambda time the
frequency so this is a general formula
relating velocity Lambda and
frequency and let's see let's plug it
into here
now let's get rid of the frequency
frequency is C ided by
Lambda so frequency is
C ided by
Lambda and then there's another C down
here and we get the bry's equation that
the momentum is pl's constant divided by
the wavelength the smaller the
wavelength the larger the
momentum if you want a beam of particles
with very high momentum give it a small
wavelength or to say it the opposite way
if you want a very short wavelength
particle it's at the cost of having that
particle have a large
momentum momentum and wavelength are
inverse to each
other so now let's let's go back
to wants to measure or wants to get a
roughly speaking he wants to get a
photograph of the electron where the
electron is uh not fuzzy on scales
larger than Delta a
just wants to take a photograph of the
electron or it doesn't have to be an
electron it could be a a golf ball
doesn't matter what it is wants to get a
photograph of it and wants the
photograph to be non fuzzy on a certain
scale Delta X well every photographer
knows that or anybody who understands
anything about waves and images and so
forth knows that the form an image which
is
precise or nonone fuzzy to size Delta X
you have to use wavelengths that are
shorter than Delta X if you try to make
an image of a golf ball with a radio
wave a radio wave of let's say 10 m the
golf ball will look fuzzy on the scale
of 10 m if you're try to do it with a
wavelength of a tenth of a of a tenth of
a golf ball a 10th of a CM the golf ball
will look pretty
good so the rule is
that Lambda the wavelength of the
light must be less than Delta X if you
want to get an image with Precision
Delta X now I erased that equation the
equation that I erased is that the
momentum is equal to plun constant ided
Lambda so now Heisenberg was caught in a
bind if he wants to measure the position
to a high accuracy Delta X he's got to
use a
um he's got to use a high momentum
electron has to use a short wavelength
electron if he wants Delta X to be
smaller than a centim then he's got to
be using a wavelength smaller than a
cenm but if he's using a wavelength
smaller than a cenm that means the
momentum of the photon has to be larger
than H over 1
cm so the smaller do
X the larger the momentum of the photon
that he has to use to make the image the
shorter the wavelength of a photon that
he has to use to make the image if
Lambda is small then p is going to be
large well now what does that mean that
means that we're going to wind up
bombarding this
object with a high momentum Photon the
high momentum Photon may make a very
good image of the position
but then it's going to collide with this
and knock it off in some random
Direction knock it off in a random
Direction with a
momentum uncertain uncertain momentum of
order of magnitude of this momentum
here this particle will come in and just
like the photon hitting the slit it will
get knocked in some random
Direction and so the conclusion will be
that immediately after you try to
measure the position
immediately
afterwards the momentum has become very
uncertain it has been kicked hard having
been kicked hard if you measure its
momentum afterwards it will have nothing
to do with the momentum
beforehand so you cannot determine both
the position and the momentum at the
same
time measuring the position necessarily
imparts a random momentum a kick a
random momentum kick to the
particle result is whatever the momentum
is was beforehand it won't be that
afterwards uh and that's another example
of the fact that there's no such thing
as a gentle
determination in qu
mechanics well you can do a gentle
determination but it will be a very
imprecise determination
In classical physics incidentally oh
keep in mind uh why what about classical
physics why is it different In classical
physics the reason is because light
doesn't come in discrete packets In
classical physics we've used the fact
that that light comes in discrete
indivisible Quantum discrete indivisible
photons and if we have a wavelength
then there's a minimum amount of energy
that can be that can go with that
minimum amount of momentum that can go
with that
wavelength namely one Photon you can't
have less than a single Photon In
classical physics energy does not come
discreete multiples of some basic unit
and so you can do the same experiment
with as uh small an energy as you like
you it's as though in classical physics
you could subdivide that Photon into
arbitrarily small units of energy take
just one of
them with the same wavelength and form
an image with it in quantum mechanics
you're always
stuck by the fact that the energy of a
light wave comes in these discrete
packets and that discret packet if it
has wavelength Lambda will have a
momentum H over Lambda and therefore
give this an inevitable k
of a m h over Lambda now
that's this
is several
examples of the same kind of thing that
doing experiments in quantum mechanics
is different than doing experiments In
classical mechanics you can always
imagine classical mechanics doing a very
gentle experiment that doesn't disturb a
system and then just go on from there
and do a later
experiment uh and do a later experiment
the early ear experiments not having
influenced the outcome of the later
experiments so for example you can
measure the position and that and that
not affect the outcome of a later
detection of the Velocity which is not
true in
quants
uh these are a lot of examples but the
examples add up to a
uh to a if you like a notion that the
basic logic of classical mechanics is
incorrect basic underlying logic is not
sufficient to understand measurement
process in quum
mechanics um the whole setup is wrong
the whole setup not just not just
particular it's not just each experiment
you can go and analyze it and try to
figure out what's wrong with it and try
to correct for it no the whole
underlying structure of classical
physics is inadequate to discuss Quant
mechanical phenomenon uh let's take a
break for 5 minutes and uh then
start Quant mechanics
proper okay uh somebody asked me about
how do you measure the velocity of a
particle uh the answer is gently first
of
all here's a simple here's a simple
conceptual way to do it velocity or
momentum momentum let's suppose we know
the mass of the particle so but by uh
that by measuring its um velocity we
also measure its
momentum a simple conceptual way to
measure velocity is to measure um
location at two different times and then
take the difference of location that's
how far it travels and divide by the
time between measurements and that's the
velocity that's the way you would
measure velocity now you have to be
careful you want to measure the you want
to measure the position twice in
succession but you don't want to measure
the position with such with such good
with such a good determination that it
gives a random kick to the velocity
which is what you're trying to measure
you wouldn't want to measure the
velocity by beginning the experiment
with a random kick which randomizes the
velocity and sends it off in some
direction very different uh than it was
moving with to begin with Direction and
velocity so your your two measurements
of velocity
sorry of position should be very gentle
measurements that don't change the
velocity very much or that don't change
the momentum very much that means that
they must be done with photons of very
long
wavelength if you don't want your first
initial detection of the location of
this particle to uh to uh to to give it
a good whack then you want to do it with
a very long wavelength Photon a long
wavelength Photon will then tell you
only that the electron is in some region
of size
Lambda okay so what you know then is the
position of the electron X let's say
plus or minus
Lambda meaning to say that there's an
uncertainty of magnitude Lambda then you
wait a really really long time until the
electron has moved a long long
ways that has some velocity it started
out with some velocity you've you've
changed the velocity only by a very
small
amount by using a very long wave length
Photon so we take the wavelength of the
photon to be so long that there's been
an unappreciable change in the momentum
and then at a much later time we
discover that the particle is at X plus
or minus Lambda maybe even plus or minus
Lambda plus VT
it's velocity times the time between the
two
measurements so true there's a little
bit of sloppiness in the measurement of
the positions a large sloppiness excuse
me in the measurements of the positions
and that's going to lead to a sloppiness
in the distance that the particle moves
what's the sloppiness the
sloppiness the distance that the
particle will move will be
VT plus a
sloppiness of order
Lambda and we take Lambda to be very big
so that uh so that we don't disturb the
velocity very much then how do you find
this is this is how far the particle
moves let's call it D distance that it
moves in order to find the velocity we
have to divide the distance that it
moves by the time so let's divide it by
the time
this isn't this is now a measurement in
the sloppiness of the Velocity the
sloppiness of the Velocity measurement
is Lambda / T no matter how big Lambda
is if we wait long enough if we let T be
very very large then the sloppiness and
the velocity can be made small so the
way we measure the velocity is by taking
a long time to to do it do very very
gentle measurements of the position so
that we don't whack the
velocity and in that way we can measure
the velocity with great Precision
however it's been at the cost of knowing
where the particle
is the particle is not been determined
to a Precision better than Lambda the
velocity has been determined to a
Precision of something like Lambda over
T so whatever you do you'll never be
able to determine both the position and
the Velocity in the same experiment to
do one and not the other one or the
other kind of quantum
mechanics
yeah
yes well
um I say it again yeah
uh let's see you wait a very long time
so
that uh
that's the that's because you're taking
this to be the uncertainty and the
velocity but there's also an uncertainty
from here that has to do with the
original
setup let me think about it you I
understand your question let let me
think about it uh and uh come back to
you with an answer
um yeah it's a good let me let me come
back to
it
yeah MH
yes I see I see yes you can
um you can determine the position of
this wall by averaging over a long
period of time with photons B many many
photons banging off
it yeah yeah
I'm uh I'm
um trying to remember what I was going
to talk about we'll come back to the
uncertainty principle for sure but I I'm
I've lost the thread of my
thought
um all right so I I I forgot what I was
going to say but let's just move on
so the fundamental logic of quantum
mechanics is not the same as the
fundamental logic of classical mechanics
and that shows up at the earliest
possible stage namely what do you mean
by the state of a particle what do you
mean by the
configuration what do you mean by uh
knowing everything that there is to know
about a system or everything that can be
known about a
system in classical
mechanics the space of States what we
call the phase space we had some various
versions of it in one version it was
just a set of
points I use the word set and I use the
word set on purpose a set of points the
states of a
system heads Tails or 1 2 3 4 5 six for
a
die uh in particle mechanics or
mechanics uh more that's a little bit
less primitive than this very simple
system here it's phase space the states
of a system are phase space PS and X's
PS and
X's uh points in a phase space are the
states of a system but again the
collection of possible states of a
system form a set they form a set they
form a set of points and the basic logic
of classical physics of classical pH
space is set
theory
um sets of points describe the possible
states of a system and transitions or
motions from one point of in that set to
another point in that set describe the
mechanics or the Dynamics of a system in
Phase space it's the flow through phase
space what exactly is a state a state is
a point in that set a member of the set
an X and A P for
particle a point H or t for heads and
tails or a bunch of PS and X's for
General system of many particles but a
point or a member of a
set now you could think of something a
little more General and possibly call it
a
state uh in which you introduce a bit of
statistics a bit of probability or a bit
of uncertainty from the beginning you
might say look I uh my apparatuses do
are not sufficient to determine with
infinite Precision the position and
velocity of a particle so instead of
doing that I will
say the particle is somewhere is in some
little region here or I might assign a
probability distribution a probability
distribution is a function of X and P
which might be peaked at the center here
and fall off as you move away from it
and so forth a probability distribution
on phase space might even be a more
General version of what you mean by the
state of a
system but if I told you that the notion
of a state of a system is a probability
distribution I think most of you will
come back and say yeah but you know if I
look more carefully at the system if I
look more carefully I can always reduce
that probability
distribution and I can always get as
close as I like by doing delicate
experiments and again in classical
physics doing experiments which don't
disturb the system terribly much doing
experiments on the system which will get
it to be closer and closer to a point so
when you speak about a statistical
distribution you're as being a state
you're not talking about the maximum
amount of knowledge that you could have
about a system you you're talking about
an imp a um a practical limitation
because of the coarseness of your
apparatuses and so forth might force you
to use a probability
distribution and only talk about things
to within a Precision that you can
measure them but uh you wouldn't think
that that was very fundamental and
eventually you would say with sufficient
accuracy in your
apparatuses that uh that the maximum you
can know about a particle corresponds to
a point in the phase space and in that
sense
States in classical physics are points
in a
set points in a
set and you can know
everything that's implied by knowing a
point in the set in particular in this
case knowing a p and an
X in quantum mechanics states are not
sets do not form sets the natur natural
way of manipulating States and asking
questions about them is not set theory
is not state is not set
theory states are
vectors in a vector space in quantum
mechanics quite a different mathematical
object than a
set a vector space is mathematically
extremely different than a set and in
order to understand quantum mechanics
this is not some
abstraction that is really um sort of
unnecessary to understanding the subject
this is so Central that uh that that to
not talk about it we would completely
miss the basis of the basics of quantum
mechanics
what in order to understand the logic of
quantum mechanics we have to understand
the mathematics of um Vector spaces
we're just forc to it there's no way
around
it if I tried to do things without it
I'd be
faking so let's talk about Vector spaces
now the use of the term Vector oh these
are vector spaces linear Vector spaces
every Vector space is
linear so linear is a redundant word but
they Vector spaces over the complex
numbers that may mean nothing to you
right now but it will as we go along
Vector space the space of State
the state
space space of
states is not a
set but it is a vector
space now the use of the word Vector can
be in vector vector space over the
complex numbers
over C C stands for the complex numbers
and I'll tell you exactly what this
means if you don't know what it means
don't worry because you will
know okay first of all most of us are
familiar with the notion of
vector uh from the classical notion of a
pointing of a thing pointing in a
direction in ordinary three-dimensional
space with a certain
length what I'm talking about is not
vectors in space in that
sense uh these are abstract vectors in
abstract Vector spaces which have
nothing to do with your naive concept of
a vector in space as an arrow pointing
in some direction in space with a given
length uh when I teach this I
usually make a linguistic distinction
between Vector spaces and pointers in
space which are the things you usually
think about as vectors uh I I I can
never quite figure out how to do this
without getting everybody confused
including
myself I will try as much as possible
when I'm talking about a
three-dimensional Vector in Space the
kind of vector that could correspond to
Velocity or position or momentum and
that sort of thing I'm going to use the
term pointer Whenever there is any
ambiguity about what I'm talking about a
poter meaning a a direction in ordinary
three-dimensional space together with a
length I'll use use the term pointer in
order to not get confused with a
completely different mathematical
concept or not a different mathematical
to a much more General mathematical
concept called a vector space a vector
space is a space of vectors but of
course these vectors are not pointers in
ordinary Direction ordinary space
pointers in ordinary space are a special
case of vector spaces but not the
special case we're going to be
interested
in Okay so let me tell you what a vector
space is first of all it's a collection
of mathematical objects called
vectors again I emphasize over and over
not vectors in or just abstract objects
called vectors maybe I should change
their name and not the name of the
vectors in three-dimensional space we
could go we could call them wectors or
uh or schmeets but
uh but uh one way or another we've got
to
uh make some distinctions all right it's
a collection of
objects which we can
label let's label them we can also label
sets by points and give the points
labels like a b and c and so forth but
now I'm labeling vectors and to indicate
that they are vectors of the right
kind namely the kind that come into
quantum mechanics we're going to
draw a a symbol like that this is called
a k
Vector was called a k vector by
durak uh there's another kind of vector
called a bra vector and if you put them
next to each other they make a braet or
a
bracket that's where the name came from
but we'll come to brackets in a little
while it's half a bracket a bracket
being what happens when you put a bra
next to a cat is that clear
yeah okay okay so there's a collection
of
objects collection of objects called
vectors
okay now what does it mean to say it's a
vector space over the complex
numbers what it means is that first of
all you can multiply vectors by complex
numbers now the ordinary vectors in
ordinary space are a vector space over
the real numbers if I have a vector for
example
three units of length pointing in the
direction North by Northwest that are 45
de to the uh to the horizontal that
would define a pointer if you like all
right so ordinary three-dimensional
pointers uh have a length and a
direction you can multiply them by
Numbers if you multiply a certain Vector
this one here this sorry a certain poter
by two it just gets twice as long in the
same
direction if you if you multiply it by
minus1 it's the same length but pointing
in the opposite direction if you
multiply it by 7 and A2 it becomes s and
a half times as
long so you can multiply a ve a pointer
a pointer by an ordinary real number
positive or
negative mathematicians would say that
pointers form a vector space over the
real numbers vectors over the real
numbers meaning to say that you can
multiply them by real numbers and when
you multiply them by a real number you
get another pointer
back we're going to make a
generalization of that idea where
vectors can be multiplied by complex
numbers now eventually we'll see some
examples there's nothing like an example
to uh to make it clear but what that
means is that given any Vector you can
multiply it given a you can multiply it
by any complex number let's use use for
complex numbers let's use the Greek
alphabet so if Alpha is any complex
number every I assume everybody here is
familiar with complex numbers I'm going
to assume that I'm not going to teach
you complex numbers here you can
multiply any vector by a complex number
Alpha and it's still and it's a new
Vector not the same Vector it's another
Vector so the operation of multiplying
by a comp complex number is well defined
in a complex Vector space we can call
this B for
example multiplying by Alpha Maps every
Vector into another
Vector Alpha being any complex number
that's the first property of a vector
space over the complex numbers sometimes
we can call it a Hilbert I mean
sometimes it's just called a Hilbert
space uh Vector space is over the
complex number a Hilbert space Hilbert
was a
mathematician so that's the first
property given a vector you can multiply
it by any complex number and it's a new
Vector the second
property is that if you have two vectors
any two vectors let's call them a and
and
B you can add them and you get another
Vector so adding vectors give new
vectors now first of all here's
something which is really these both of
these
things are really new when you go from
classical mechanics to quantum mechanics
in classical mechanics the notion of a
state is a point in a in a in a space of
points in other words in a set it
doesn't make any sense to
multiply uh points in a set by a number
for example let's take heads and tails
what does it mean to multip mly heads by
three or heads by a complex number
doesn't mean anything you just have two
points heads and tails and that's all
you have uh you don't have a thing that
you would call three times heads or or
minus three times heads or 2 + 4 * I *
heads so in saying that state Vector
that states of a system are a vector
space this is something new and radical
and weird you should not understand this
at this point unless of course you've
done quantum mechanics before this
should not make any sense at all but for
the moment we're doing some abstract
mathematics to get some definitions and
then I'll show you how those definitions
uh apply so first of all you can
multiply a vector an abstract vector by
any complex number and you get a new
Vector that's an operation that you can
do and the next operation is that you
can add any two vectors now of course if
you can add any two vectors and you can
also multiply them by complex numbers
then you can
also then you can also multiply the
first vector by a complex number the
second vector by a complex number and
that gives you some new I won't call it
C I'll call it C
Prime
so what you can do with a vector space
is you can take any pair of vectors
multiply both of them by arbitrary
complex numbers add them and you get a
new Vector so the no of addition is well
defined of course for ordinary pointers
the notion of addition is also defined
and it's defined by the
operation of drawing the
parallelogram ordinary vectors satisfy
both of these rules that you can
multiply a vector by any real number I'm
sorry not complex numbers ordinary
pointers as I said are vector spaces
over the real numbers and that means
that you can multiply any of them by a
real number and you can add any pair of
any pair of pointers to get a new
pointer so ordinary pointers in space
are a special case of a vector space
over the real
numbers let me give you a couple of
other
examples in particular Vector spaces
over the complex numbers this was the
reason Hilbert originally invented the
notion of Hilbert space to describe
functions functions of X let's say
functions of one
variable for Simplicity that's the
simplest
example take the class of functions of
one variable X let's take X to be the
variable but complex function functions
of one variable functions s of
X which are the sum of two terms let's
call it a real part s real of X where s
real of X always takes on real values
plus I I being the square < TK of minus1
times the imaginary part of
s every complex number is a sum of a
real part plus an imaginary part and
every complex function now this is a
function of only one variable it's not a
function of a complex variable it's a
function of an ordinary variable but the
function itself can be
complex all right so this means that for
every point x there is a complex number
s of
X or equivalently two real
functions now let's take any complex
function let's take any complex function
like this we can multiply it by a
complex number any complex
number defines a new
function you can multiply the complex
number S Plus s real plus I S imaginary
by a complex number Alpha in other words
complex numbers can be multiplied and
therefore you can take any complex
number
and multiply it by any
function so first of all functions of X
satisfy the first
rule the collection of functions the
collection of functions of X the
collection of complex functions of X
form a vector
space that's the that's the assertion
we're going to check that first of all
you can multiply any function by a
complex number and you get a new
function all right so it satisfies rule
number one what about rule number two
you can take any pair of functions and
add them together and you get a new
function so if you have two functions s
and fi let's call
them that's another function a perfectly
good
one so S and F are complex functions
there sum is a complex function that's
enough to tell you
that complex functions are a vector
space over the complex
numbers real
functions are a vector space over the
real numbers but they're not a vector
space over the complex numbers why not
because you can't multiply a real
function by a complex number and get
back a real function you'll get back a
complex function you don't get back a
real function so complex functions form
a complex Vector space and that's the
that actually is this the vector space
that uh that Hilbert was first
interested
in that's an example of a Hilbert space
it's an important example in quantum
mechanics maybe the most important
example but for now I'm just uh
illustrating uh the uh the abstract
mathematical
definitions complex functions of X form
a vector space over the complex
numbers let me give you another one
it's uh very
similar
let's let's invent a thing called a
column Vector a column Vector is just a
collection of numbers which have and we
can decide how many we fix the number of
numbers uh 1 2 3 any number we like but
let's fix it and we simply arrange them
in a column let's call those numbers
let's give them let's call them a one A2
A3 and
A4 this would be a vector space of
Dimension
four we could also think of vector
spaces of Dimensions two a one 1 and A2
there's pairs of numbers pairs of
complex numbers here's quadruples of
complex numbers we could make quintuples
of complex numbers sextuples of complex
numbers and we could even imagine
infinite uh Columns of complex numbers
or just one complex number just one
complex number one unit long A1 of X all
of these each one separately not all
together but each one separately four
dimensions or two Dimensions or three
dimensions each of these form the
collection of such
objects form a complex Vector
space Vector space over the complex
numbers so let's take this particular
complex Vector space here A1 A2 A3 A4
where where the A's are arbitrary
complex
numbers if these are arbitrary comp
complex numbers and we display them in a
column like
this then I assert that there are rules
which will allow this to be a vector
space so what are the rules I'm going to
invent now a rule of addition notice so
far there has been no rule of
multiplication of vectors only addition
of vectors so the rule for adding two
vectors here's two vectors one I'll call
a the other one I'll call B B1 B2 B3 B4
just add the entries this is the
definition of adding
of column vectors A1 + B1 A2 + B2 A3 +
B3 A4 plus
B4 obviously with this definition if you
take any two vectors and you add them
you get another
Vector the A's and B's are arbitrary
comp Lex numbers okay but each
specification of four complex numbers
defines a
vector you are two vectors one labeled a
one labeled B here's a third one that
you can make out of
it all right so I started uh for some
reason I started with the addition rule
here but it's also true that we can
invent the idea of multiplication by a
complex number if we want to take a
vector let's call it A1 A2 A3 and A4
and multiply it by the complex number
Alpha we just do that by multiplying
every entry by alpha alpha A1 Alpha A2
Alpha a whoops Alpha A3 and Alpha
A4 we multiply every entry by the same
number that defines
multiplication by a complex number and
all I've done is multiply complex
numbers here
obviously given any vector and any
complex number I can make another vector
by multiplication not multiplication of
vectors but multiplication of numbers by
vectors and given any two vectors you
can add them so the collection of
objects arranged in a column this
way also form a vector space now if I
were to take the collection that
consists of vectors of length two length
three length four and combine them all
together that's not a vector space
because I haven't given you any rule for
adding a vector with with length two to
a vector of length three I haven't told
you how to do that and I don't see any
obvious rule for that so it's uh with
this set of
rules the collection of two dimensional
vectors three four the whole shebang
does not form a vector space but for a
given length fix the length it forms a
vector space and the terminology is that
it forms a vector space in this case of
Dimension
four now of course this has an analog
for ordinary
pointers for pointers we can just think
of these as the components of the
pointer along the different axes pick
some axes X Y and Z and pointers have
components
so we can also specify an ordinary
pointer by specifying a collection of
components a collection of components
along different axes and that uh that
also defines a uh a
pointer so it's natural to call these
numbers the components of a
vector and we'll come back to the
uniqueness of components
you can if you like think of such a
column as a
function of the index variable here well
let's let's get that's too abstract
let's let's drop that for the moment
we'll come back to it be thought of as a
function but uh we don't need
to now of course I've told you nothing
about in what possible sense what
possible sense can it make to identify
vectors with states of systems we're not
going to do that tonight tonight we're
just going to talk about uh about the
abstract notion of a vector tonight and
a bit of next week we'll talk about the
abstract notion of a vector and then
we'll talk about how Vector spaces
Define uh the states of a system and
then go on and work out uh some examples
of of quantum mechanical systems
described by such Vector spaces at the
moment this should be sort of um mumbo
jumbo right success H success what
success in in making mumbo jumbo no I
think I've given you rather accurate
definitions that you can understand of
what vectors
are and how to manipulate them how to
how to manipulate them how to do the
abstract operations with them these
abstract operations are in many ways
analogous to the abstract oper ation
that you do with set theoretic logic
with Boolean
logic these abstract these abstractions
for how you manipulate Vector spaces are
the generalizations if you like of how
Boolean set theory allows you to ask uh
allows you to combine Concepts together
and or all these ideas have some meaning
in uh set theory was and and is you take
two sets and you combine them and make
the union of them or you take the
intersection or is it the other way it's
the other way isn't it it's the other
way sorry and is the intersection or is
the uh is the union of two sets the
analogous logic in quantum mechanics
doesn't operate on sets it acts on
Vector spaces so it's best that we get
rid that we go through Vector spaces
once and for all it's the basic
underlying mathematics and once we get
familiar with it it won't seem so uh so
much mumbo jumbo but in the moment we're
doing abstract mathematics any other
question okay so let's continue with the
abstractions
now there's a notion of every for every
such Vector space well let's let's leave
this here there's a notion of a dual
Vector
space the Dual Vector space is in one to
one correspondence with the original
Vector space well let's go back a step
let's just talk about complex
numbers for complex
numbers incidentally complex numbers are
themselves a vector space you can
multiply complex numbers by a complex
number you can add complex numbers
they're just the case of one dimension
onedimensional Vector spaces over the
complex numbers are just the complex
numbers now there's an operation that
you can do on complex numbers which is
called complex
conjugation it's a very important
operation and all it is if you think
about the cartisian plane if you think
about the complex
plane the real part of a number being on
the horizontal
axis and the imaginary part being on the
vertical axis
then the number then is
described by a real part the real part
is the horizontal
component and the uh the imaginary part
is the vertical component and we would
just write that this number usually
called Z is equal to x + i
y the complex conjugate number is just a
number reflected
about the
horizontal if this is a number called Z
X+ i y then x minus iy is called Z
Star xus i y is the complex conjugate of
X Plus i y or Z star is the complex
conjugate of
Z Let's uh let's manipulate something
let's let's consider the product of Z *
Z
Star Z * Z Star what is
it it's equal to x + i
y * x - i
y That's
x^2 now we get ixy and then we get minus
ixy from the cross terms they cancel and
then + y^ 2 why did I write + y^ 2
because I * - I is + 1 I * I is -1 so I
* - I is
+1 Zar Z is X2 + y^2 what is X2 + y^2 X2
+ y^2 is the square of the length of
this hypotenuse
here so Z Star Z is the square of the
length or the square of the magnitude of
the number or its distance from the
origin
so complex conjugation is a convenient
uh operation among other things the
complex conjugate times a number is uh
the mag square of the magnitude of the
number
um
and if you're not most of you of course
are quite familiar with complex
conjugation I want you to think of it as
a very very basic operation
but more than that I want you to think
of it as a mapping of the numbers back
into the numbers given any number any
complex number you can map it to its
complex
conjugate what about Vector spaces I
think we should probably quit now I
think it's time to quit now next time
we'll go through a little more about
Vector spaces Vector spaces
operators uh Herm Mission operators and
igen
values and then we'll begin applying it
the quantum mechanical
[Music]
problems the proceeding program is
copyrighted by Stanford University
please visit us at stanford.edu